giving delivery date a whole new meaning
this video looks at the potential
benefits of dates for labor and delivery
during childbirth
check it out
[Music]
in the 19th chapter of the quran
mary is giving birth to jesus
i didn't even know jesus was in the
quran the things they don't teach you in
hebrew school
it says the pains of childbirth drove
her to the trunk of a palm tree she
cries out and she is answered by gabriel
archangel and evidently obstetrician who
knew shake the tree he says and it will
drop upon you ripe fresh dates and
you'll be all better no epidural
necessary do dates really help with
labor and delivery it would take a
little over 2 000 years but researchers
finally decided to
put it to the test
that's some anecdotal evidence that
dates might be helping but they wanted
to know for sure whether the addition of
date fruit for the last few weeks of
pregnancy would reduce the need for
labor induction or augmentation that's
where you give drugs to induce uterine
contractions to initiate or accelerate
labor
it's one of the most commonly performed
obstetrical procedures in the u.s
dramatically increasing over the last
few decades from less than 10 of
deliveries to now nearly a quarter
there are certainly legitimate medical
indications but are often done just for
convenience
and not necessarily the convenience of
the patient but the provider who may
also have perverse financial incentives
and other reasons to want to speed
things along
and dates might not help with those
factors but might they help foster a
normal spontaneous delivery let's
find
out a prospective study women eating six
dates a day that's totally doable during
their last month of pregnancy versus no
dates at all and
the women who consumed date fruit had
significantly better cervical dilation
significantly higher proportion of
intact membranes that's a good thing and
spontaneous labor occurred in 96 of
those who consumed dates compared to 79
of women in the non-date group with
significantly less drugs used and the
labor was shorter as in about seven
hours shorter overall
it is therefore concluded that the
consumption of date fruit in the last
four weeks of pregnancy significantly
reduced the need for induction and
augmentation of labor the results
weren't a randomized controlled trial
wait what
the women weren't randomized
they even talk about how it was hard to
find women who had agreed to not eat
dates because it's part of their
cultural beliefs
so you can totally imagine how there
could be all sorts of differences
between the women who ate dates and
those who agreed to go without that
could account for the findings
maybe the date eaters were more
religious or or higher socioeconomic
status or who knows i mean yeah you
could argue you know what's the downside
might as well give dates a try but
that's not good enough i want to know if
they actually work
but there never been a randomized
controlled trial
until three years later
the effect of late pregnancy consumption
of date fruit on so-called cervical
ripening in first-time mothers
in the last few weeks of pregnancy
hormonal changes cause the cervix the
opening to the uterus to start to ripen
to soften so that when the contractions
start it can more easily dilate open
at this stage the cervix loses its
integrated structure and therefore
becomes soft and dilated as soon as
strong contractions begin
through a ripe cervix you can push a
baby out with like 20 pounds of pressure
per square inch but if the cervix isn't
there yet it can acquire more like
200 pounds of pressure so it goes
without saying the cervical ripening
before the onset of labor is important
if you want a normal vaginal delivery
the search for a safe inexpensive and
easy method of facilitating cervical
ripening is therefore of great interest
so
let's randomize a few hundred women
starting at like their 37th week to eat
about six dates a day or not
until their first contraction
cervical ripening is rated with what's
called a bishop score normally a score
of five or less
indicates an unfavorable cervix whereas
eight or more and you're good to go and
the average bishop score on the women
randomized to the date group was
significantly higher closer to eight
whereas the date free group was down at
around five
and the surface was more dilated in the
date group and hey
dates are healthy anyway so maybe dates
should be recommended for pregnant women
to help with cervical ripening
particularly in the last few weeks of
their pregnancy
a randomized controlled trial of
hundreds of pregnant women found that
having women eat around six dates a day
for a few weeks before giving birth can
significantly improve cervical ripening
the the readiness of the cervix the
opening to the birth canal you can also
use drugs or surgery to prep the cervix
oxytocin is the most common agent
you may have heard doctors talking about
pitocin that's the brand name although
it's effective its use is associated
with multiple potential adverse side
effects which can affect both the mom
and the baby
if only there were a safe simple side
effect free solution well
dates may fit the bill
the use of oxytocin for labor induction
in the date group was less than half
that of the control group and the few on
dates that were induced had more
successful deliveries
an earlier study in which prior day
consumption appeared to shorten labor by
more than six hours speculated that
maybe dates themselves have
oxytocin-like effects
all right how about a head-to-head trial
comparing the efficacy of dates versus
oxytocin in the management of postpartum
bleeding
postpartum hemorrhage excessive blood
loss after birth
is one of the major complications of
pregnancy and the leading cause of
maternal mortality
as the placenta peels off the uterus
it's supposed to contract to stop the
bleeding
and if it doesn't if the uterus doesn't
have sufficient muscle tone
you can give an injection of oxytocin to
help squeeze off the blood loss
like all drugs though can have side
effects sometimes causing a dangerous
drop in blood pressure
there's also various devices that can be
inserted to apply pressure and worse
comes to worst surgery
but why not try fruit first
available cheap side effect free yeah
but does it work
they set up a randomized clinical trial
to find out
immediately after the placenta comes out
women were given a one-time dose of like
five dates or an intramuscular shot of
oxytocin and then they just collected
all the blood to see which worked better
overall uh three hours after delivery
the blood loss average in the date group
was significantly less than in the
oxytocin group by about a quarter of a
cup
check this out see how the date group
was mostly in the lowest category under
two-thirds of a cup of blood loss
whereas the drug group was mostly about
a cup or more
conclusions
use of oral dates i don't know how else
you take them after delivery decreased
bleeding more than intramuscular
oxytocin and it's a good alternative in
normal delivery but wait if dates have
oxytocin-like effects to contract the
uterus shortening labor by helping to
induce earlier uterine contractions
might date consumption increase the risk
of premature labor
i guess we'll never know until
now
the effect of date fruit consumption on
the length of gestation
starting at about 38 weeks women were
randomized to eat seven dates a day or
not
and
eating dates did not affect delivery
dates but what it did do is
significantly reduce the need to hasten
labor with drugs half of the non-date
group had to be drugged versus 30
percent less than the seven dates a day
for a week grew an induction of labor is
serious business it can increase
complications such as bleeding
c-sections
urine hyper
and even uterus rupture
and apart from the complications women
who are induced tend to feel less
satisfied with their birth experience
therefore
date consumption in late pregnancy is a
safe supplement to be considered as it
reduced the need for labor intervention
without any adverse effect on mother and
child
the only thing we're missing now is a
double-blind study not just a randomized
trial but a placebo-controlled
study right i mean the women in the date
group obviously knew they were eating
dates and maybe that had some kind of
placebo effect
the only double-blind study i could find
on dates and delivery is in arabic but
the english abstract describes how women
just entering their active labor phase
were given a date syrup or placebo ah
that's brilliant right hard to make a
placebo date but you could make some
kind of placebo syrup like a molasses or
something right
note when they say honey date syrup
they're not talking about a syrup of
honey and dates but a syrup made out of
honey dates which is a soft melt in your
mouth variety easy to whip into a syrup
and normal labor progression was
evidently higher in the date group
around
compared to less than 70 in both the
placebo and control groups and labor
duration was also shorter in the date
group like two hours shorter so on your
due date maybe we should give dates
there do
[Music]
you